Matthew T. Adams

matthew@matthewadams.me • http://matthewadams.me

https://www.linkedin.com/in/matthewadams • https://stackoverflow.com/story/matthewadams • https://github.com/matthewadams

Summary

Pragmatic, polyglot, senior software engineer, architect, team leader & mentor with over 3 decades of hands-on experience, ready to serve as chief technology officer, executive technical leadership, or continued senior contributor and mentor.

Technologies

JVM: Kotlin, Java, AspectJ, Spring, Maven, Gradle

Node.js: JavaScript, TypeScript, NPM, Yarn, Express, Koa, Hapi

Database: MongoDB, Cassandra, Redis, SQL

Messaging: Kafka, MQTT, AMQP Containers: Docker, Kubernetes, Helm

Cloud: GCP, AWS, Azure

Source control: Git, Mercurial, SVN, Perforce

CI/CD: GitLab, GitHub, Jenkins, CircleCI, TravisCI, Release Management, SDLC

Architecture: Reactive Streams, CQRS, DDD, Event Sourcing, Event-Driven, Microservices, REST, WebSockets

Experience

Northscaler (formerly SciSpike), Austin, TX

Principal Consultant: August, 2012 to present

- Provided software architecture and development services to Northscaler clients
- Published numerous Northscaler open source libraries
- Founding co-committer of Spring Data Cassandra, https://spring.io/projects/spring-data-cassandra
- Wrote custom courseware for Spark, Node.js, Scala, Spray, Akka HTTP, git & more
- Wrote trait-based framework in Java via AspectJ to facilitate extreme productivity on subsequent client Java projects

Matthew Adams Consulting, Austin, TX

Principal Consultant: January, 2009 to August, 2012

Client: Electronic Arts, Austin, TX (August, 2011 to August, 2012)

- Provided Java development services for next-generation and existing highly-scaled gaming platform, including database sharding, migration from Hibernate to vendor-neutral JPA, and work on various other stories
- Technologies: Java, Spring, OSGi, Equinox, Virgo, JPA/Hibernate, JDBC, JMS, JUnit, TestNG, Maven, EasyMock

Client: Financial Dynamics, Denver, CO (June, 2010 to July, 2011)

- Provided development services in Java & C# for new features and enhancements to trading information systems
- Technologies: Java, Spring, Spring Batch, Maven, JUnit, C#, .NET, SQL Server, Visual Studio, NUnit, Microsoft Test

Client: Pierce County Information Technologies, Tacoma, WA (January to June, 2010)

- Provided Java development services for new features and enhancements to legal information systems
- Technologies: Spring, Java, AspectJ, Servlets, JPA/OpenJPA, JDBC, JSP, Jetty, JUnit, Maven, AJAX, Ext JS

Client: Statera, Bellevue, WA (November, 2009 to January, 2010)

- Provided Java development services to confidential Statera client integrating Amazon's Mechanical Turk platform.
- Technologies: Java, Servlets, JSP, Hibernate, Spring

Client: Pierce County Information Technology, Tacoma, WA (March, 2009 to November, 2010)

- Awarded contract to build AJAX-based, RIA paperless court order system
- Gathered requirements for, designed and built foundation for rewrite of county legal information system
- Technologies: Java, JEE, Spring, Jetty, OpenJPA, JUnit, Maven, Ant, AspectJ, AJAX, Ext JS, Sybase, BIRT, XML

Client: Avue Technologies, Tacoma, WA (February to March, 2009)

- Provided design & implementation guidance on database and web controller refactoring
- Diagnosed and resolved production memory issues
- Technologies: Java, JEE, EJB, Servlets, JSP, Hibernate, Spring

Client: Nilistics, Seattle, WA (February, 2009)

- Provided design recommendations and developed inversion of control build framework product
- Technologies: Ant, Java

SpringSource (now Pivotal), San Mateo, CA

Senior Consultant: August, 2007 to January, 2009

Technologies: Spring Framework, Spring MVC, Spring WebFlow, Java, JEE, Servlets, Hibernate, JPA, JDO, JDBC, JSP, JMS, JMX, JTA, Tomcat, JUnit, Ant, Maven, OSGi

- Conducted public and private classes nationwide on the Spring Framework, Spring MVC, Spring WebFlow, Hibernate and more
- Created training courseware for several SpringSource training courses, including student labs and slides
- Provided technical marketing collateral for the SpringSource marketing department, including technical articles & slides, screencasts, datasheets, demos and FAQs

Matthew Adams Consulting, Tacoma, WA

Independent Consultant: May, 2007 to August, 2007

Client: F5 Networks, Seattle, WA (July to August, 2007)

- Collaborated on F5 knowledge base application
- Integrated Spring MVC with Communiqué
- Technologies: Java, JEE, Spring, Communiqué, Servlets, JSP, Tomcat

Client: the Platform, Seattle, WA through Cypress Consulting, Seattle, WA (June to July, 2007)

- Collaborated on digital media asset delivery project
- Technologies: Java, JEE, Spring, Ant, Maven, JUnit, Tomcat

Client: Muse, Seattle WA (May, 2007)

- Consulted on architectural best practices on the use of transparent persistence with IDO and IPA
- Technologies: Java, JEE, JDO, JPA, JUnit

Xcalia (now Progress Software), Paris, France

Senior Consultant & Product Marketing Manager: July, 2006 to May, 2007

Consultant: August, 2004 to July, 2006

Technologies: Java, J2EE/JEE, Servlets, JSP, Spring, JDO, JPA, Tomcat, EJB, JUnit, Ant, Maven

- Created new corporate web site using Spring MVC, JSP and JDO on Tomcat
- Served in capacity of consultant, sales engineer, and product marketing manager
- Promoted Xcalia's products through technical demonstrations, presentations at technical conferences, and presence in numerous online technical forums
- Participated in strategic business partnership identification and evaluation
- Collaborated on marketing of product line, its features, and direction

The Cobalt Group (now ADP Dealer Services), Seattle, WA

Enterprise Architect: March, 2004 to August, 2004

Technologies: Java, J2EE, WebLogic, Servlets, JSP, EJB, JDO, JUnit, Ant

- Performed detailed domain-driven analysis of Cobalt's vertical market
- Worked with architecture team to establish software architecture, development, and process standards
- Oversaw the redesign effort of the automobile inventory service, a Cobalt core enterprise service

Travelport Corporate Solutions (now Orbitz), Seattle, WA

Senior Software Engineer/Architect: July, 2000 to March, 2004

Technologies: .NET, C#, ASP.NET, IIS, SQL Server, NUnit, XML, XSL, Java, J2EE, Tomcat, JBoss, EJB, JDO, JESS/Rules Engine, JUnit, JMS, Ant, UML

- Designed and implemented a new corporate travel policy enforcement service
- Refactored home-grown transparent persistence framework
- Integrated Travelport's legacy, XML-based logging system with log4net
- Analyzed, designed, and prototyped persistent domain object model for Travelport client organization, corporate travel
 policy, and fine-grained application-level security
- Designed and prototyped new enterprise system for corporate travel services, with a custom JMS-based workflow engine
- Created comprehensive Ant-based build for new architecture, including JUnit-based testing
- Developed Java Cryptography Architecture (JCA) component to enable secure single sign-on (SSO) between Travelport's legacy components and custom client systems
- Supported portal development team with refactoring of custom content management server

Red Sky Interactive (now Designory), Irvine, CA

Senior Java Developer: March, 2000 to June, 2000 Technologies: Java, J2EE, EJB, WebLogic, UML

• Led the design of marine e-commerce website for Red Sky client

First Horizon Merchant Services (now Elavon), Englewood, CO

Windows/Internet Software Engineer: October, 1996 to February, 2000

Technologies: Java, J++, COM, MTS, ASP, MIDL, Win32, C, C++, MFC, SQL Server, Poet FastObjects

- Created web-based merchant credit card transaction search engine
- Instituted company-wide development standards on the full software development life cycle
- Performed design & code reviews for all projects to ensure adherence to standards
- Designed and developed credit card transaction dispute management persistent domain object model and intranet web-based application in Java/J++ and ASP using an ODMG-compliant ODBMS and SQL Server
- Designed and implemented web presentation tier framework for both intranet and Internet web sites, encompassing look-and-feel, site navigation, and integrated security
- Ported MFC-based C++ credit card processing application from 16 to 32-bit
- Designed and implemented plug-in framework for above application in order to import and export credit card transaction data in arbitrary formats

J.D. Edwards (now Oracle), Denver, CO

Programmer/Analyst: February, 1995 to October, 1996

Consultant, February, 1995 to July, 1995 Technologies: C, C++, MFC, Java

- Led the OneWorld installation software team
- Refactored existing C code base to leverage object orientation using Visual C++ and MFC
- Researched integration of OneWorld product with emerging Java technologies
- Served on Internet deployment team for www.jdedwards.com

MEG Laboratory, University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, Denver, CO

Programmer/Professional Research Assistant: January, 1993 to February, 1995

Technologies: C, MATLAB

- Created laboratory website
- Developed software in C and MATLAB to analyze neuroanatomical structures on Solaris
- Created sophisticated 3D neuroanatomically correct renderings for publication
- Coauthor of three published research papers on neurological MEG

Matthew Adams Consulting, San Diego, CA

Independent Consultant: January, 1992 to April, 1992

Technologies: C, MS-DOS, Basic

Client: Pyxis, San Diego, CA

- Provided cost-to-benefit analysis application to sales department
- Enhanced MedStation product to include transaction data export facility

The Quantum Leap, San Diego, CA

Programmer: October, 1989 to July, 1991

Technologies: dBase/FoxBase, C

Contributed to various client engagements under principal consultant

Professional Affiliations

Member, Java Community Process:

- JSR 12, Java Data Objects 1.0 (JDO)
- JSR 220, Enterprise JavaBeans 3.0 (EJB), Java Persistence API 1.0 (JPA)
- JSR 243, Java Data Objects 2.0 (JDO)
- JSR 317, Java Persistence API 2.0 (JPA)

Member, CommonJ Service Data Objects 2.1 Specification Group (SDO)

Education

Bachelor of Arts in the Cognitive Sciences, University of California at San Diego, 1991